D.K. "Dock" Martin papers, Inclusive: 1916-1968, undated, Bulk: 1938-1954
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
D.K. "Dock" Martin papers
Inclusive: 1916-1968, undated, Bulk: 1938-1954
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
222
Martin, D.K. "Dock"
15 document boxes.
The D.K. "Dock" Martin papers contain materials relating to D.K. Martin, a Texas public official and Baylor University fundraiser and booster. Martin raised money for various historic Baylor buildings, including Rena Marrs McLean Gymnasium, Tidwell Bible Building, Alexander Residence Hall, Morrison Hall, Armstrong Browning Library, and Marrs McLean Science Building.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
D.K. Martin was born in Johnson County, Texas, on 1878 January 17, but moved to Hill County later. He attended Baylor University, graduating in 1900. An excellent athlete while in college, Martin won the first Field (Track) Day medal awarded by Baylor to a student. After graduation, Martin moved first to Itasca, then to San Antonio, where he worked as an insurance salesman and real estate agent. He married Mary Woodall Martin in 1904, and they had one son, Edward W. Martin.
Martin was a member of the Texas State Highway Commission for eleven years under Governors Ross Sterling and Dan Moody, 1925-1936. This service and the efficiency of the highway system at this time was a source of considerable pride to Martin. He was mentioned more than once as a possible candidate for governor during his service on the commission.
In addition to his political life, D.K. Martin is remembered for his long service to Baylor University as a fundraiser, member of the Board of Trustees, president of the Baylor Alumni Association, administrator, and Baylor booster. His fundraising activities alone continued for over 30 years, including involvement as chairman of the 1920s Greater Baylor campaign, 1940s Tidwell Bible Building campaign, and an active member of the Baylor Centennial Foundation. Although involved with many Baylor activities, he was closely involved with fundraising for Rena Marrs McLean Gymnasium, Tidwell Bible Building, Alexander Residence Hall, Morrison Hall, Armstrong Browning Library, Marrs McLean Science Building, and other associated buildings. He also was involved with fundraising for Baylor athletics.
Martin retired from business and moved to Waco in 1957, where he continued his active involvement with Baylor. D.K. Martin died in Waco on 1965 August 18.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the activities of D.K. Martin, longtime Baylor fundraiser and booster. Documents in this collection are primarily letters to and from Martin, with many notable Baylor names from the 1920s-1950s, including Pat Neff, Carr P. Collins, Earl Hankamer, and others. Many of these letters describe Martin's vision of growing Baylor University, and others' opinions on fundraising and building campaigns. Other correspondence includes letters from his time as highway commissioner. Many letters towards the end of his life describe Martin's political views, and how they were different from that of his friends.
While the vast majority of the collection is correspondence, there are legal papers from the Kokernot family, clippings about Martin's career, and various other documents from Martin's life and career. There are also drawings and descriptions of a roadside park near San Antonio, dedicated to D.K. Martin in 1937.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, this collection was arranged in folders with titles and some date ranges. Folders were already arranged in existing unnamed groups, with some materials organized in some groups alphabetically, others topically. These groups became series in the most recent round of processing. Most of the existing folder titles were kept as well. Within each folder, materials are in original order, not necessarily chronologically.
Currently, the D.K. "Dock" Martin Papers are arranged in two series: I. Correspondence and II. Personal Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 222. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Pat M. Neff collection, Inclusive: 1847-1952, Bulk: 1920-1947
Earl Curtis Hankamer papers, Inclusive: 1909-1972, undated, Bulk: 1940-1970
Related references
Baylor Alumni Association. "History of BAA." Accessed 2014 March 31.
"Latest 'Baylor Line' Dedicated to D.K. Martin, Board Member." Lariat (Waco, TX), 1948 December 3.
"Name D.K. Martin to Lead Baylor's State-Wide drive," Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 June 28.
"Waco, Texas Citizens-Last Name Beginning with 'MA-MF,'" The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
"Well-Known Benefactor of BU Dies." Waco News-Tribune (Waco, TX), 1965 August 19. In "Waco, Texas Citizens-Last Name Beginning with 'MA-MF," vertical file.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Neff, Pat Morris, 1871-1952.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baptist General Convention of Texas -- History.; Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Baylor University -- History -- 20th century.; Baylor University -- Presidents.
Subjects
Baptist universities and colleges -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Correspondence.; Research notes.
- Correspondence, 1916-1964; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Poor.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains letters written to or by D.K. "Dock" Martin during his career as insurance salesman, real estate agent, Baylor fundraiser, and highway commissioner.
  - Letters Alphabetically, 1916-1964; 1
    General condition: Unknown.
    - A, 1931-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B, 1920-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - B, 1932-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Brancho, M.E., 1936-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bryan, Alva, 1937-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cantrell, J.C., 1955-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Collins, Carr P. (1 of 3), 1930-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Collins, Carr P. (2 of 3), 1930-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Collins, Carr P. (3 of 3), 1930-1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Collins, Carr P. (1 of 4), 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Collins, Carr P. (2 of 4), 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Collins, Carr P. (3 of 4), 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Collins, Carr P. (4 of 4), 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Connally, Tom: (1 of 3), 1931-1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Connally, Tom: (2 of 3), 1931-1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Connally, Tom: (3 of 3), 1931-1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - D, 1936-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Daniel, Price, 1951-1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Dealey, G.B., 1936-1942, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - E, 1931-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Ely, W.R., 1931-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - F, 1924-1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fleming, William: (1 of 2), 1940-1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Fleming, William: (2 of 2), 1940-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - G, 1930-1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Gentry, Brady, 1937-1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Gilchrest, Gibb: (1 of 2), 1935-1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Gilchrest, Gibb: (2 of 2), 1935-1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Haden-Hobby: (1 of 3), 1931-1962 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Haden-Hobby: (1 of 3), 1931-1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Haden-Hobby: (1 of 3), 1931-1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Hodges-Hunter: (1 of 2), 1933-1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (1 of 7), 1933-1959 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (2 of 7), 1933-1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (3 of 7), 1933-1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (4 of 7), 1933-1959 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (5 of 7), 1933-1959 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (6 of 7), 1933-1959 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (7 of 7), 1933-1959 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (1 of 5), 1940-1961 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (2 of 5), 1940-1961 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (3 of 5), 1940-1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (4 of 5), 1940-1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Hankamer, Earl: (5 of 5), 1940-1961 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Hendrick, T.G., 1931-1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Hooks, Pat: (1 of 2), 1932-1946 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Hooks, Pat: (2 of 2), 1932-1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - J, 1937-1960 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - James, E.S., 1958-1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Johnson, Lyndon: (1 of 2), 1950-1961 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Johnson, Lyndon: (2 of 2), 1950-1961 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - K, 1931-1947 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Kemp, L.W. (1 of 4), 1916-1955 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Kemp, L.W. (2 of 4), 1916-1955 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Kemp, L.W. (3 of 4), 1916-1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Kemp, L.W. (4 of 4), 1916-1955 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Kleburg: (1 of 3), 1932-1959 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Kleburg: (2 of 3), 1932-1959 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Kleburg: (3 of 3), 1932-1959 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Kokernot: (1 of 3), 1930-1948 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Kokernot: (2 of 3), 1930-1948 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Kokernot: (3 of 3), 1930-1948 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - L, 1932-1962 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Landes, James H., 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - M: (1 of 2), 1936-1962 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - M: (2 of 2), 1936-1962 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Mc: (1 of 2), 1936-1962 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Mc: (2 of 2), 1936-1962 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - McCall, Abner, 1958-1963 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Moody, Dan: (1 of 2), 1928-1959 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Moody, Dan: (2 of 2), 1928-1959 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Moore, Charles: (1 of 2), 1932-1952 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Moore, Charles: (2 of 2), 1932-1952 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - N, 1933-1961 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Neff, Pat: (1 of 3), 1921-1937 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Neff, Pat: (2 of 3), 1921-1937 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Neff, Pat: (3 of 3), 1921-1937 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Neff, Pat: (1 of 4), 1938-1942 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Neff, Pat: (2 of 4), 1938-1942 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Neff, Pat: (3 of 4), 1938-1942 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Neff, Pat: (4 of 4), 1938-1942 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Neff, Pat: (1 of 3), 1943-1950 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Neff, Pat: (2 of 3), 1943-1950 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Neff, Pat: (3 of 3), 1943-1950 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - O (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - O’Daniel, W. Lee: (1 of 2), 1939-1947 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - O’Daniel, W. Lee: (2 of 2), 1939-1947 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Penland, G.H., 1934-1958 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - P-Q, 1917-1964 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - R, 1936-1954 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - S: (1 of 2), 1931-1962 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - S: (2 of 2), 1931-1962 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Stevenson, Coke, 1938-1948 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - T: (1 of 2), 1931-1952 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - T: (2 of 2), 1931-1952 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - U-V, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - W: (1 of 3), 1931-1960 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - W: (2 of 3), 1931-1960 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - W: (3 of 3), 1931-1960 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - White, W.R. (1 of 4), 1948-1958 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - White, W.R. (2 of 4), 1948-1958 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - White, W.R. (3 of 4), 1948-1958 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - White, W.R. (4 of 4), 1948-1958 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Y, 1938-1962 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Letters by Subject, 1924-1963; 2
    - Baylor Dental College, 1944-1946 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Armstrong Browning Library (1 of 3), 1938-1953 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Armstrong Browning Library (2 of 3), 1938-1953 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Armstrong Browning Library (3 of 3), 1938-1953 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Baylor Finances (1 of 4), 1931-1959 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Baylor Finances (2 of 4), 1931-1959 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Baylor Finances (3 of 4), 1931-1959 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Baylor Finances (4 of 4), 1931-1959 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Soliciting Building Funds for Baylor, 1937-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Baptist Foundation of Texas (1 of 3), 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Baptist Foundation of Texas (2 of 3), 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Baptist Foundation of Texas (3 of 3), 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Baylor Athletics, 1927-1963 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Baylor Board of Trustees (1 of 2), 1938-1962 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Baylor Board of Trustees (2 of 2), 1938-1962 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Martin: Baylor Building Committees (1 of 3), 1937-1958 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Martin: Baylor Building Committees (2 of 3), 1937-1958 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Martin: Baylor Building Committees (3 of 3), 1937-1958 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Baylor, General, 1931, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Highway Commission: Appointment Congratulations (1 of 2), 1930 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Highway Commission: Appointment Congratulations (2 of 2), 1930 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Highway Commission: General (1 of 3), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Highway Commission: General (2 of 3), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Highway Commission: General (3 of 3), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Highway Commission: Official Matters (1 of 2), 1924-1940 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Highway Commission: Official Matters (2 of 2), 1924-1940 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Insurance A-M (1 of 3), 1926-1933 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Insurance A-M (2 of 3), 1926-1933 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Insurance A-M (3 of 3), 1926-1933 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Insurance N-Z (1 of 2), 1931-1933 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Insurance N-Z (2 of2), 1931-1933 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Moving of Baylor Medical School to Houston, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Moving Baylor University from Waco to Dallas, 1958-1959 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Personal Business and Financial (1 of 2), 1931-1933 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Personal Business and Financial (2 of 2), 1931-1933 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Political (1 of 2), 1931-1964 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Political (2 of 2), 1931-1964 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Real Estate (1 of 2), 1949 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Real Estate (2 of 2), 1949 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Personal Materials, 1924-1968, undated; 2
  General condition: Good.
  This series contains various materials on Martin's life and career, including subject files, newspaper clippings, reports, legal papers, and other associated materials. Many of the subject files include correspondence about the topic.
  - Subject Files, 1924-1962; 1
    - Baylor Dental College, 1944-1946 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Armstrong Browning Library (1 of 3), 1938-1953 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Armstrong Browning Library (2 of 3), 1938-1953 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Armstrong Browning Library (3 of 3), 1938-1953 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Baylor Finances (1 of 4), 1931-1959 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Baylor Finances (2 of 4), 1931-1959 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Baylor Finances (3 of 4), 1931-1959 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Baylor Finances (4 of 4), 1931-1959 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Soliciting Building Funds for Baylor, 1937-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Baptist Foundation of Texas (1 of 3), 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Baptist Foundation of Texas (2 of 3), 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Baptist Foundation of Texas (3 of 3), 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Baylor Athletics, 1927-1963 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Baylor Board of Trustees (1 of 2), 1938-1962 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Baylor Board of Trustees (2 of 2), 1938-1962 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Martin: Baylor Building Committees (1 of 3), 1937-1958 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Martin: Baylor Building Committees (2 of 3), 1937-1958 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Martin: Baylor Building Committees (3 of 3), 1937-1958 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Baylor, General, 1931, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Highway Commission: Appointment Congratulations (1 of 2), 1930 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Highway Commission: Appointment Congratulations (2 of 2), 1930 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Highway Commission: General (1 of 3), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Highway Commission: General (2 of 3), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Highway Commission: General (3 of 3), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Highway Commission: Official Matters (1 of 2), 1924-1940 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Highway Commission: Official Matters (2 of 2), 1924-1940 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Insurance A-M (1 of 3), 1926-1933 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Insurance A-M (2 of 3), 1926-1933 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Insurance A-M (3 of 3), 1926-1933 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Insurance N-Z (1 of 2), 1931-1933 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Insurance N-Z (2 of 2), 1931-1933 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Moving of Baylor Medical School to Houston, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Moving Baylor University from Waco to Dallas, 1958-1959 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Personal Business and Financial (1 of 2), 1931-1933 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Personal Business and Financial (2 of 2), 1931-1933 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Political (1 of 2), 1931-1964 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Political (2 of 2), 1931-1964 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Real Estate (1 of 2), 1949 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Real Estate (2 of 2), 1949 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1930-1968; 2
    - Personal, Circa 1936 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Baylor Trustee, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Highway Commission, 1930-1936 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Highway Commission (1 of 2), 1936 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Highway Commission (2 of 2), 1936 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Collected Materials, 1924-1964, undated; 3
    - D.K. Martin Park, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Highway Commission Report, 1924-1925 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Invitations and Programs, 1951-1964 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Citations and Tributes (1 of 2), 1931-1945 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Citations and Tributes (2 of 2), 1931-1945 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Published Materials, 1931-1961 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Texas History (1 of 2), 1936-1938, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Texas History (2 of 2), 1936-1938, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Political Writings, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Kokernot Legal Papers, 1936-1946 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Baylor Legal Papers, 1937-1939 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Highway Commission Certificates, 1930-1931 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Personal Legal and Financial, 1936-1942 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Personal Reports, undated (Box 14, Folder 15)